Finding Aid for Hussey Family papers, 1876-1926
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Hussey Family papers 1876-1926
Hussey family.
851534 Aa 2
William Joseph and Ethel Fountain Hussey family of Ann Arbor, Michigan. Correspondence, diaries, scrapbooks, photographs and other materials relating especially to Hussey's activities as professor of astronomy and director of the astronomical observatory at the University of Michigan, including his scientific visits to South America and South Africa.
8.5 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Allis F. Hussey (donor no. 913 ) in 1941. Additional materials came from the University of Michigan Astronomy Department (donor no. 1465 )
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
William Joseph Hussey was born on August 10, 1862 near Mendon, Mercer Co., Ohio. He was a graduate of the University of Michigan College of Engineering, class of 1889. That same year, he was appointed instructor of mathematics and astronomy. From 1892 to 1896, Hussey was professor at Stanford University, then from 1896 to 1905, he was astronomer in the Lick Observatory at the University of California. He returned to the University of Michigan in 1905 as professor of astronomy and director of the Detroit Observatory. From 1911 to 1917, he was also director of the Observatory and professor of geodesy in the Argentine National University of La Plata. He died on October 28, 1926 in London, England.
Ethel Fountain Hussey was active in Ann Arbor and University of Michigan organizations and activities, most notably the Michigan League (of which she was first president) and the Association of Collegiate Alumnae.
The Hussey family collection divides between the papers of William Joseph Hussey and his wife Ethel Fountain Hussey. The William Joseph Hussey papers includes correspondence, papers relating to his astronomical work, travels abroad, and affairs at the universities where Hussey held appointments, particularly The University of Michigan. Of interest are two letterpress books, two University of Michigan student notebooks containing notes on John William Langley's course in physics and notes on mathematics, account books, scrapbooks, and diaries of Argentina and South Africa travels and activities in The University of Michigan Observatory. The papers of Ethel Fountain Hussey include correspondence, diaries, and subject files relating to her organizational activities, her early work with the Michigan League and with the Association of Collegiate Alumnae. Some of the couple's correspondents included James B. Angell, Levi L. Barbour, Luther Burbank, Marion L. Burton, William W. Campbell, William L. Clements, Ralph H. Curtiss, David Starr Jordan, Robert P. Lamont.
Subjects:
Africa.; Ann Arbor (Mich.); Astronomy--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Scientists--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; South America.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Astronomy.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Observatory.; Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Albums.; Astronomical observatories.; Fountain family.; Hussey, Ethel Fountain, 1865-1915.; Hussey, William Joseph, 1862-1926.; University of Michigan. Observatory.; Universidad Nacional de La Plata. Observatorio Astronómico.
Contributors:
Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Barbour, Levi L. (Levi Lewis), 1840-1925.; Campbell, William Wallace, 1862-1938; Clements, William L. (William Lawrence), 1861-1934.; Curtiss, Ralph Hamilton, 1880-1929.; Hussey, Ethel Fountain, 1865-1915.; Hussey, William Joseph, 1862-1926.; Jordan, David Starr, 1851-1931.; Lamont, Robert Patterson, 1867-1948.; White, Myrtle E.
Genre Terms:
Albums.; Cyanotypes.; Daguerreotypes.; Diaries.; Photographs.; Tintypes.; Scrapbooks.
- William Joseph Hussey
  - Correspondence 1876, 1880-1926 (Box 1)
    - 1876, 1880-1886, 1889 (Box 1)
    - 1891-1920, 26 folders (Box 1)
    - 1921-1926 undated, 14 folders (Box 2)
    - 1922 with daughter Allis (Box 2)
    - Correspondence received upon his death 1926 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence with R.P. Lamont 1906-1921, 8 folders (Box 2)
  - Postcards (Box 2)
  - Topical files
    - Biographical/bibliographical material (Box 2)
    - Board of Regents 1904-1923, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Clippings (Box 2)
    - Committee on University Publications (Box 2)
    - Double stars (articles) (Box 2)
    - Genealogical material (Box 2)
    - Holden (E.S.) and University of California 1897, 5 folders (Box 3)
      (the first folder includes a selective item listing of the contents of these files prepared by a researcher)
    - Invitations and programs (Box 3)
    - La Plata memoranda and article (Box 3)
    - Lantern slide presentation notes
      - Mt. Wilson 1921 (Box 3)
      - Royal Astronomical Society 1922 (Box 3)
      - "Stars and Telescopes," 1917 (Box 3)
      - Yerkes Observatory 1921, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Lecture, "A trip to other worlds" by Edwin B. Frost (Box 3)
    - Membership certificates (Box 3)
    - Schaeberle (John Martin) paper (Box 3)
    - Trip to Pittsburgh and Chicago (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous writings, notes, letters of recommendation (Box 3)
  - Diaries, 1908-1911, 1913-1916, 1918-1920, 1922-1923, 1925-1926, 15 volumes (Box 3)
  - Diary of South Africa trip 1923-1924 (Box 3)
    (original and copy)
  - Student notebooks
    - 1882 (Box 4)
    - 1884 (Box 4)
    - 1880-1881, 3 volumes (Box 4)
  - Letterbook 1896-1903 (Box 4)
  - Scientific observation books, 2 volumes (Box 4)
    (1 volume concerns Lick Observatory management)
  - Account Book 1897-1904 (Box 4)
  - Scrapbooks, 3 volumes (Box 4)
  - Scrapbooks, 6 volumes (Box 5)
  - Diplomas, citations, and engraving of W.J. Hussey, 9 items (Folder 1)
- Ethel Fountain Hussey (also includes W.J. Hussey)
  - Correspondence 1880-1915 (Box 7)
    - 1880-1913, 37 folders (Box 6)
    - 1914-1915, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Topical files
    - Association of Collegiate Alumnae 1909-1919, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Association of Collegiate Alumnae, Ann Arbor branch 1908-1910 (Box 7)
    - Collegiate alumnae (elsewhere) (Box 7)
    - South America diary, 1911-1912 (Box 7)
    - Student Christian Association 1910-1911 (Box 7)
    - White (Myrtle) correspondence 1910-1911 (Box 7)
    - Women's League 1909-1910, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Manuscript of articles and stories, 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 6 folders (Box 7)
    - Student essays, 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Diaries (Box 8)
  - Notebooks (Box 8)
  - Exercise books (Box 8)
  - Genealogy and Griffin family letters (Box 8)
- Photographs
  - Cased photographs: Fountain family (Box 9)
  - Album: Fountain family (Box 9)
  - Ethel Fountain Hussey (Box 10)
  - W.J. Hussey-Portraits, formal and informal (Box 10)
  - W.J. Hussey-group pictures with colleagues (Box 10)
  - W.J. and Ethel F. Hussey-photographs taken on voyage to Argentina 1911 (Box 10)
  - Fountain family (Box 10)
  - Hussey family (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous (include Detroit Observatory) (Box 10)
  - Slides made from photographs in album 1980 (Box 10)
  - LaPlata Observatory, 24 items (Box 10)